Mss.B.B445
American Philosophical Society
Max Bergmann papers, [ca. 1930]-1945
Mss.B.B445
American Philosophical Society
7.5 Linear feet 7,500 items
7,500 items, 7.5 linear feet.
Papers consist of letters, reports, addresses and lectures, relating to biological chemistry and other scientific topics, the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, refugee scientists, professional associations, etc.
Bass, Lawrence W., (Lawrence Wade), 1898-
Beadle, George Wells, 1903-1989
Bergmann, M., (Max), 1886-1944
Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
Cattell, Jacques, 1902-1960
Cattell, James McKeen, 1860-1944
Cohn, Alfred E., (Alfred Einstein), 1879-1957
Dakin, H. D., (Henry Drysdale), 1880-1952
Dubos, René J. (René Jules), 1901-
Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946
György, Paul, b. 1893
Landsteiner, Karl, 1868-1943
Langmuir, Irving, 1881-1957
Loewi, Otto, 1873-1961
MacInnes, Duncan Arthur, 1885-1965
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987
Osterhout, W. J. V., (Winthrop John Van Leuven), 1871-1964
Robbins, William Jacob, 1890-1978
Rous, Peyton, 1879-1970
Uber, Fred Murray, 1905-
Urey, Harold Clayton, 1893-1981
Van Slyke, Donald Dexter, 1883-1971
Waksman, Selman A., (Selman Abraham), 1888-1973
Weaver, Warren, 1894-1978
Box 1-23
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research and accessioned, 1964 (Accession #150.1ms.)
Biographical/Historical note
Max Bergmann (February 12, 1886-November 7, 1944) was a biochemist, whose research proved key for the study of biochemical processes. His work on peptide synthesis and protein splitting provided a starting point for modern protein chemistry and the study of enzyme-substrate interactions. He is most noted for developing the carbobenzoxy protecting group, for the synthesis of oligopeptides, using any amino acid in any sequence. He co-authored with his colleague Joseph S. Fruton (1912-2007, APS 1967) several reviews in protein and enzyme chemistry, notably “Proteolytic Enzymes,” in the Annual Review of Biochemistry 10 (1941): 31-46 and “The Specificity of Proteinases,” in Advances in Enzymology 1 (1941): 63-98.
Bergmann was born in Fürth, Germany, the son of a coal merchant named Solomon Bergmann and his wife Rosalie Stettauer. He entered the University of Munich, initially interested in botany, but shifted to chemistry, after being convinced that biological questions could only be answered by the methods of organic chemistry. He received a bachelor’s degree in 1907, and afterward became a student of Emil Fischer (1838-1914, APS 1909), the foremost protein and carbohydrate chemist of the day at the University of Berlin. In 1911 Bergmann received a Ph.D. with a dissertation on acyl polysulfides and became Fischer’s research assistant. In 1912 Bergmann married Emmy Miriam Grunwald with whom he had two children. The marriage ended in divorce, and he remarried Martha Suter in 1926. During World War I Bergmann was exempted from military service because of his research work with Fischer. While working with Fischer, Bergmann made important contributions to carbohydrate, lipid, tannin and amino acid chemistry, developing new methods for the preparation of α-monoglycerides. In 1920 Bergmann was appointed Privatdozent at the University of Berlin and head of the chemistry department at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Textile Research.
Bergmann left the University of Berlin in 1921 to become the director of the new Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Leather Research and Professor of chemistry at the Dresden Technical University. At Dresden, Bergmann created one of the world’s leading laboratories for the study of protein chemistry. After Adolf Hitler’s rise to power, Bergmann, a Jew, emigrated to the United States. From 1934 until his death Bergmann was affiliated with the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research in New York.
Bergmann represents the tradition of German organic chemistry applied to biological problems. Working with his mentor Fischer, who sought effective methods to separate and identify amino acids, and who identified the peptide bond as the structure that connects amino acids, Bergmann made many basic contributions to protein and amino acid chemistry. In Dresden he extended Fischer’s work of separating and identifying the amino acid constituents of proteins. In order to establish the conjecture of some protein chemists that proteins were, in fact, polypeptides, containing thousands of amino acids, Bergmann developed new methods of peptide synthesis. The most important discovery came in 1932, when he and his colleague Leonidas Zervas created the carbobenzoxy method allowing them to use any amino acid in any sequence to produce peptides and polypeptides that closely resembled naturally occurring proteins.
Bergmann continued this work in New York at the Rockefeller Institute, stressing two new lines of research: (1) expanding the carbobenzoxy method to form peptides that could serve as substrates for protein-splitting enzymes, and (2) unraveling the total structure of proteins. After becoming head of the chemistry laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute in 1937, Bergmann recruited several talented biochemists. Along with his colleague Joseph Fruton, he discovered the first synthetic peptide substrates for which several enzymes were catalysts. When they demonstrated that the enzyme pepsin was able to catalyze the hydrolysis of synthetic peptides, they implicated the peptide bond in protein structure, but also provided the first clear evidence that specific enzymes split peptides at exact linkages in the chain. Their discovery cleared the path for study of how enzymes act as catalysts for every biological function.
Bergmann’s methods of analysis and synthesis proved incapable of solving the riddle of protein structure. He applied methods for separation and quantitative analysis to every amino acid in a protein in an attempt to establish their sequence in the polypeptide chain. In 1938 he proposed a theory of the systematic recurrence in the location of every amino acid residue in the peptide chain of a protein. However, his hypothesis proved an oversimplification. Two biochemists in his working group, Standford Moore and William Stein, showed him that the analytical data did not support his “periodic theory,” and Bergmann was forced to abandon it. Moore and Stein later collaborated in developing novel methods for quantitative analysis of amino acids in protein hydrolysates, methods they perfected after World War II. By 1949 it was possible to determine the order of the links of each amino acid in a protein. The Englishman Frederick Sanger was the first to establish the complete amino acid sequence in a protein, the hormone insulin. Moore and Stein followed by identifying the sequence of a more complex protein, the enzyme ribonuclease.
Bergman died of cancer in New York City on November 7, 1944. His mastery of peptide synthesis and protein splitting constituted the beginnings of modern protein chemistry. Bringing to the United States a background in German organic chemistry, he laid the foundations for the work of others, who would fulfill Bergmann’s goal of understanding and mapping the molecular structure of proteins and enzymes. His research colleagues found him a supportive leader and collaborator. He coauthored a number of publications with other members of his research group.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
Max Bergmann, formerly director of the Kaiser-Wilhelm Institute for Leather Research, joined the Rockefeller Institute in 1933; he was one of many German scientists of the intellectual migration. A protege of Emil Fischer, Bergmann had developed in Germany a leading center for protein chemistry, attracting students from around the world. His successful career continued in his new homeland, which he considered "the best country on the globe" (Letter to Felix Haurowitz, 8 July 1943). His research program, which focused on the action of proteolytic enzymes on synthetic peptides and on the problem of protein structure, aimed at explaining the biological specificity of proteins. As determinants of specificity, proteins were then generally regarded as the active hereditary material in the chromosomes; Bergmann's investigations were also intended to account for this genetic specificity. The Bergmann Papers -- letters, reports, addresses, and lectures -- are therefore important not only for the history of biochemistry, but also for the history of molecular genetics.
The correspondence shows Bergmann to be a central figure within the international network of protein chemists, and instrumental in helping other emigre biochemists in the 1930s. The letters also document the importance of Bergmann's laboratory as a training center; among his young assistants were Stanford Moore and William H. Stein, who developed sensitive techniques of chromatography. In addition to basic work on proteins, Bergmann remained associated with leather research, and the collection contains material on this link between academic biochemistry and commercial leather research in America.
American Chemical Society ( Notices of meetings for the Divisions of Organic Chemistry, Biological Chemistry, and Agricultural Chemistry. Congratulations on Bergmann becoming a member of the society. Includes materials on symposia on nutrition; invitations to speak at various local sections.) Correspondence (6 folders) 1934-1944 English
American Leather Chemists Association ( Membership application forms, notices of annual meetings, ballot sheets for electing members, officers, and voting on society policies. Copy of proceedings. Thanks for giving speeches.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1934-1945 English
Astbury, William Thomas, 1898-1961 ( Correspondence regarding Bergmann's theories of animal protein structure, requests for reprints, and reviews of each other's papers prior to publication.) Correspondence (12 items) 1934-1939 English
Ballentine, Robert ( Science and professional communications. Correspondence regarding publication of research, letters of recommendation, vita, application, interview, impressions of Bergmann.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1940-1944 English
Bergmann, M. (Max), 1886-1944 ( Correspondence with and about German refugee scientists. Among the scientists mentioned are Hermann K. Mohr, Francis Krauss-Sterrett, and Ruth Crzellitzer.) Correspondence (50 items) 1941-1944 German
Chargaff, Erwin, 1905-2002 ( Correspondence regarding a chemical, questionnaire needed for Chargaff to be employed with the U.S. National War Production Board.) Correspondence (4 items) 1942-1943 English
Chibnall, Albert Charles, 1894-1988 ( Professional activities related to protein chemistry, Chibnall's visit to the laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1938-1943 English
Clark, William M. (William Mansfield), 1884-1964 ( Technical issues in protein chemistry. Manuscript sent to Clark describing method developed in Bergmann's lab on measurement of solubility an a semi-micro scale.) Correspondence (2 items) 1942 English
Clarke, Hans Thacher, 1887-1972 ( Includes materials on the network of protein chemists. Personal correspondence, requests for reprints, recommendations regarding Konrad Bloch, Heinrich Waelsch, Chi-yuan Chou, Heinz Fraenkel-Conrat, Hans J. Cahmann, and Joseph Fruton. Analyses from Hermann Fischer sent to Clarke's lab. Manuscript to be published in Journal of Biological Chemsitry.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1934-1944 German
Cohn, Edwin J. (Edwin Joseph), 1892-1953 ( On scientific and administrative issues, including materials on the campaign to establish a separate section on protein chemistry within the American Chemical Society (see also a file on "Protein Committee", circa 1930s).) Correspondence (2 folders) 1937-1941 English
Demerec, M. (Milislav), 1895-1966 ( On the 1941 Cold Spring Harbor Symposium.) Correspondence (4 items) 1941 English
Du Vigneaud, Vincent, 1901-1978 ( Scientific and social matters. Recommendation of Dr. Loring and list of Loring's publications. Information on chemicals and preparations. Letters concerning filling positions at the Rockefeller Institute and George Washington University. Meeting, dinner invitations. Requests for reprints. Correspondence on experiments.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1934-1945 English
Fischer, Hermann Otto Laurenz, 1888-1960 ( Scientific and social concerns. Letter from Fischer to Bergmann, desiring to free Prof. Freidrich Epstein from a concentration camp in France. Arranging lectures. Request for chemicals, chemicals sent to Rockefeller Institute for analysis. News about Bergmann's nephew in Germany. Exchange of papers. Note about Simon Flexner. Letters concerning various scientific refugees' job prospects in the United States: Otto Meyerhof, Dr. Bernstein, Prof. Strauss (a friend of F. Mendel). Bergmann's efforts to publish a paper by Mendel and Fischer in Science.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1937-1941 German
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946 ( Flexner's reaction to Bergmann's work. Progress report of the analysis of progestin. Thanks for reprints.) Correspondence (7 items) 1935-1940 English
Fraenkel-Conrat, Heinz, 1910-1999 ( Important correspondence regarding Fraenkel-Conrat's career as an emigre life scientist. Summary of an experiment sent by Fraenkel-Conrat to the Journal of the American Chemical Society, seeks advice concerning preparations of compounds. Thanks to Bergmann for providing a job recommendation and helping to secure naturalization papers. Copies of preparation methods for compounds. Correspondence concering changes in employment.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1933-1944 German
Fruton, Joseph S. (Joseph Stewart), 1912-2007 ( Professional and scientific matters. Notes on a lab demonstration given by Fruton. Work reports by both Fruton and Bergmann. Requests for reprints. Bibliography and vita of Fruton to 1942. Copy of lecture delivered by Bergmann on the occasion of Fruton receiving the Eli Lilly Award, 1944. Speech given by Fruton at Bergmann's funeral.) Correspondence (56 items) 1941-1945 English
Gasser, Herbert S. (Herbert Spencer), 1888-1963 ( Gasser was director of the Rockefeller Institute, 1935-1953. Includes: technical correspondence and response to William H. Stein's work. Request by Gasser for Bergmann's annual lab report. Notices of Institute meetings. Notes to Gasser from Bergmann concerning students in the lab: Stein, Paul Zamecnik, Robert Ballentine, Rocha de Silva, Mark A. Stahmann, Calvin Golumbic. Notices of F. Goebel and Rene Dubois becoming members of the Institute.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1936-1945 English
Hanson, Frank Blair ( Informative correspondence about Rockefeller Foundation Fellowships, including the fellowships of Klaus Hofmann, R. Ing Haugaard, and Carl Niemann.) Correspondence (23 items) 1935-1940 English
Haurowitz, Felix, 1896-1987 ( Haurowitz correspondence from Turkey, where his work contract is running out. Inquires about the fate of German scientists in the United States. Later correspondence relates to Haurowitz's immigration to the U.S.) Correspondence (8 items) 1937-1943 German
Institute for Leather Manufacture Research ( Informative material about organic chemistry of leather and tanning. Requests for Bergmann's reprints.) Correspondence (7 items) 1934-1937 German
Levene, P. A. (Phoebus Aaron), 1869-1940 ( Includes Levene's reaction to Bergmann's research and materials related to the establishment of the Protein Committee for the National Research Council. Recommendations of H. Freiburg, Hans Wurzburger, Ing Irene Adler, and Eric Schmidt. Request for chemicals.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1935-1946 English
Link, Karl Paul, 1901-1978 ( Bergmann and Link were colleagues and friends. Their many shared scientific, cultural, and social interests are documented in their correspondence. The principal importance of these files lies in the information they contain about the growth of biochemistry within an agricultural context, and the relation of Link's work to other programs. Being a renowned chemist, Link was well connected within the international community of biochemists. There is a great deal on general trends in biochemistry (including a critique of protein chemistry), and interesting exchanges related to the immigration of Carl Neuberg and Otto Meyerhof. These files are an important source on the history of biochemistry in general, and American agricultural chemistry in particular.) Correspondence (6 folders) 1934-1944 German
Meyerhof, Otto, 1884-1951 ( Reference to Mayerhof's trip to the U.S. in 1937, writes wanting to find a job. Eventually finds a job in Paris, but writes again later asking Bergmann for help. Bergmann returns a note in disguised style because of inspectors, saying that he will try and help. Later, Meyerhof's move to the University of Pennsylvania.) Correspondence (7 items) 1940-1943 German
Muller, H. J. (Hermann Joseph), 1890-1967 ( Regarding an invitation to participate in the Seventh International Congress of Genetics.) Correspondence (6 items) 1938-1942 English
Neuberg, Carl, 1877-1956 ( A response to Bergmann's work.) Correspondence (5 items) 1934-1940 German
Neurath, Hans, 1909-2002 ( On protein chemistry. Requests samples of chemicals and reprints from Bergmann. Neurath asks Bergmann's opinion on a manuscript he has prepared.) Correspondence (16 items) 1937-1943 German
Niemann, Carl George, 1908-1964 ( Various intellectual and institutional aspects of protein chemistry. Bergmann asks Niemann to recommend a chemist to work in his lab at the Rockefeller Institute. Bergmann recommends Niemann to the National Defense Board, 1943. Niemann recommended to the American Chemical Society by Linus Pauling. Death notice of Bergmann. Letter to Niemann, while at University College, London, about publishing joint papers on collagen-gelatin. Niemann discussed the London lab. Bergmann expresses his depression about his German contemporaries.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1937-1944 English
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987 ( Relates primarily to scientific and technical issues of protein chemistry. Northrop seeks a contribution for the celebration of Winthrop J. V. Osterhout's 70th birthday. Reprint requests. Letters concerning experiments, especially about chymo-trypsin.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1934-1942 English
O'Flaherty, Fred ( Leather chemistry research in the United States. Request for reprints. On Bergmann's membership in the American Leather Chemists Association. Meetings of the association and requests to speak at the meetings. Bergamann forwards a technical question from a German leather chemist. Bergmann asks O'Flaherty's help in finding a job for Grete Sicher.) Correspondence (4 folders) 1934-1944 English
Osterhout, W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven), 1871-1964 ( Bergmann's reaction to Osterhout's work. Osterhout sends Bergmann numerous reprints.) Correspondence (22 items) 1934-1942 English
Pauling, Linus, 1901-1994 ( On Carl Niemann's career, the nomination of Niemann for the American Chemistry Society award in Pure Chemistry.) Correspondence (4 items) 1941-1943 English
Perutz, Max F. ( Letters referring to the Rockefeller Foundation, meeting Bergmann in New York.) Correspondence (4 items) 1943 English
Protein Committee of the National Research Council ( On many scientific and organizational aspects of protein chemistry in America. Notices of meetings and agendas of activities. Minutes of meetings and lists of members. Letter from Charles L. Parsons to P. A. Levene, concerning a joint symposium of the Protein Committee with the American Chemical Society's Division of Biological Chemistry. Concerning a protein division for ACS.) Correspondence (26 items) 1938-1940 English
Robbins, William Jacob, 1890-1978 ( Administrative issues. Robbins requests chemicals and reprints from Bergmann.) Correspondence (4 items) 1942-1943 English
Schmitt, Francis Otto, 1903-1995 ( Material on the state of protein chemistry. Requests for reprints. Schmitt asks Bergmann to recommend a person for an opening in his lab; Bergmann recommends Hans Hirschmann.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1938-1944 English
Stein, William H. ( Various aspects of Stein's career. Technical problems of experiments while Stein is working at the Rockefeller Institute. Draft of an article by Stein and Bergmann. Office procedures and reprint lists compiled by Stein following Bergmann's death.) Correspondence (3 folders) 1936-1947 English
Stern, Kurt Guenter ( Regarding Bergmann's joining the enzyme group. Asks one of Bergmann's collaborators to speak at an informal enzyme chemistry meeting at Yale (declined).) Correspondence (10 items) 1936-1937 English
University of Michigan ( Lectures for the Summer School at the University of Michigan.) Correspondence (4 items) July 5 - 8, 1938 English
Williams, John Warren, 1898-1988 ( Williams was associated with the Division of Physical and Inorganic Chemistry of the American Chemical Society (ACS). Invites Bergmann to speak at an ACS meeting in Milwaukee (Bergmann declines).) Correspondence (5 items) 1938-1944 English
Wyckoff, Ralph W. G. (Ralph Walter Graystone), 1897-1995 ( Requests for reprints.) Correspondence (4 items) 1937-1939 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
Vincent du Vigneaud spent most of his prolific career at Cornell University Medical College in New York, where his research program focused mainly on amino acids. In the late 1930s his studies of the amino acid methionine made it possible to trace the biochemical pathway through which methyl groups were shifted from compound to compound. In the early 1940s he identified the compound biotin and deduced its chemical structure; biotin was immediately synthesized by Merck Laboratories. And in the late 1940s he isolated the active fragment of the pituitary hormone oxytocin, and within a few years worked out its amino acid composition. It was the first protein hormone ever to be synthesized, earning du Vigneaud the 1955 Nobel Prize in chemistry.
Karl Paul Link had hoped to go to medical school. Instead, with the exception of two years of post-doctoral training in Europe, his entire scientific career -- undergraduate, graduate, and fifty years of research -- was nurtured within the agricultural tradition of the University of Wisconsin. In retrospect, medicine benefited more from his accomplishments as an agricultural chemist than it would have from his practice of medicine. His discovery of Dicumarol (an important clinical coagulant), his procedures for isolating vitamins and other natural products of importance to nutrition, and his important contributions in carbohydrate chemistry (his specialty) exemplify his overlapping medical and agricultural concerns.
Link was also an influential teacher, in a sense a scientific cult figure. His analytical excellence and technical skills, matched by a charismatic personality and an open life-style, drew many students to his laboratory and home. Through his long academic lineage (among his students are Carl Niemann and Stanford Moore), Link's influence extended to other institutions, including Max Bergmann's laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute.
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.; Biochemistry -- United States.; Biochemists -- United States.; Chemistry -- United States.; Jewish scientists.; Political refugees.; Science -- Societies, etc.; Scientists - United States; Scientists, Refugee
- Papers
  - A - Misc., No. 1, 1934 May - 1939 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    A-miscellaneous, No. 1-3
    General miscellaneous materials. Job applications, invitations to meetings. Bergmann requests catalogs from instrument firms. Requests for samples of chemicals, both to and from Max Bergmann. Circulars concerning refugees and anti-Fascist campaigns.
  - A - Misc., No. 2, 1938 October - 1944 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A - Misc., No. 3, 1937 June - 1944 August (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aabye, J. S., 1935 April - June (Box 1, Folder 4)